From Ninannah to Yanome.
จากนินันนาสู่ยาโนเมะ
During the journey and upon arriving at their destination,
ระหว่างการเดินทางและตอนที่ถึงที่หมาย
Fushi received countless "stimulation"
ฟุชิได้รับ "แรงกระตุ้น" อย่างต่อเนื่อง
and received its first lesson on "consciousness".
และเกิด "ความตระหนักรู้" ซึ่งเป็นขั้นแรกของการเติบโต
Fushi, who had been imprisoned together with March, Parona, and Pioran,
ฟุชิซึ่งถูกขังไว้พร้อมกับมาช พาโรน่า และปิโอลัน
gained "consciousness".
ได้มี "ความตระหนักรู้"
It changed forms and acted out.
มันเปลี่ยนร่างและตัดสินใจทำบางอย่างด้วยตัวเอง
After that, Fushi received another "impetus".
หลังจากนั้น ฟุชิก็ได้รับ "แรงกระตุ้น" ใหม่อีกครั้ง
What will all of this accumulated information mean for Fushi?
ข้อมูลที่ถูกสะสมเอาไว้เหล่านี้ จะทำให้ฟุชิได้รับอะไรกัน
TO YOUR ETERNITY
แด่เธอผู้เป็นนิรันดร์
Come, March. Let's go home!
มาเถอะมาช กลับไปกัน
EPISODE FIVE THOSE WHO ACCOMPANY YOU
ตอนที่ 5 ผู้ร่วมทาง
You too, Grandma.
คุณยายก็ไปด้วยกันเถอะ
We're bringing Grandma back with us to Ninannah.
พวกเราจะพาคุณยายกลับนินันนาด้วยกัน
Goodbye, Mr. Bear.
ลาก่อนนะ คุณหมี
We can get to the wagon room through this waterway.
ท่อน้ำนี้เชื่อมไปยังที่จอดเกวียนสินค้า
Grandma, go on ahead with March.
คุณยายกับมาชล่วงหน้าไปกันก่อนนะ
Here's the key.
นี่คือกุญแจ
What about you, big sister?
แล้วพี่สาวล่ะ
She still has work to do. Let's go.
เขายังมีงานต้องทำ ไปกันเถอะ
Stop!
ไม่ได้นะ
What are you doing, big sister? Stop it!
พี่สาวจะทำอะไรน่ะ
I'm only going to cut off a little bit.
ฉันแค่จะตัดอะไรออกมาสักอย่าง
I need to prove to the village that the Spirit Bear is dead by showing them this.
เอากลับไปนินันนา เพื่อบอกกับคนในหมู่บ้านว่าโอนิกุมะตายแล้ว
That there is no need for the ritual to be carried out any longer.
ไม่จำเป็นต้องทำพิธีอีกต่อไป
But that's horrible!
ทำแบบนี้มันเกินไปนะ
Horrible?
เกินไปงั้นเหรอ
March, it's dead.
มาช เจ้านี่น่ะตายไปแล้วนะ
Horrible or not, it's only going to be burned and turned to ashes now.
เดี๋ยวก็คงต้องถูกเผาเป็นเถ้าธุลีแล้ว
But I feel sorry for him!
แต่มันน่าสงสารมากเลยนะ
I know.
เอาอย่างนี้ดีกว่า
March, let's play a game.
มาช เรามาเล่นเกมกัน
Go on ahead with Grandma now,
ถ้าเธอรีบไปกับคุณยายเดี๋ยวนี้
and if you do, I'll give you a reward.
ฉันจะให้ของขวัญที่พิเศษมาก ๆ เลยนะ
Look!
นี่ไง
A fluffy dog!
น้องหมาขนปุกปุยเลยนะ
March, please,
มาช ขอล่ะนะ
just this once, do as I say...
วันนี้ช่วยเชื่อฟังกันหน่อย ดีไหม
If I can prove that the Spirit Bear is dead,
ถ้ามีหลักฐานที่พิสูจน์ได้ว่าโอนิกุมะตายแล้ว
then it's possible that we can avoid
ต่อไปก็จะไม่ต้องทำพิธี
any children being sacrificed like you almost were.
และไม่ต้องมีเด็กคนไหน ต้องมาเสียสละแบบเธออีกแล้ว
But it isn't the Spirit Bear...
แต่คุณหมีตัวนี้ไม่ใช่โอนิกุมะสักหน่อย
Then think of it this way.
งั้นลองคิดแบบนี้ดูดีไหม
This bear died to protect the poor children like you from being sacrificed.
คุณหมียอมเสียสละ เพื่อช่วยเด็กที่เหมือนกับมาชไง
It died to prevent the ritual from ever happening again.
เพื่อที่จะได้ไม่ต้องมีพิธีที่ต้องสละชีวิตใครอีก
That's selfish!
พูดง่าย ๆ แบบนั้นได้ยังไงกัน
It's just a big and scary bear!
มันก็เป็นแค่คุณหมีที่ตัวใหญ่และน่ากลัว
It's not related to this!
เรื่องพวกนี้ไม่ได้เกี่ยวกับมันเลยสักนิด
No, March... You're still a child. You wouldn't understand...
ผิดแล้ว มาชยังเด็กอยู่เลยไม่เข้าใจ
Don't make that face, March...
อย่าทำหน้าแบบนั้นสิ
Big sister, why are you still laughing?
ทำไมพี่สาวยังยิ้มออกมาได้อยู่
I... I'm only trying to...
ฉันก็แค่...
Understood, March.
ฉันเข้าใจแล้วละมาช
I'll stop.
ฉันไม่ตัดแล้ว
Let's go.
ไปกันเถอะ
How do you plan to persuade the villagers?
เธอจะโน้มน้าวคนในหมู่บ้านยังไงเหรอ
I don't think it'll go well...
ฉันไม่คิดว่าพวกเขาจะยอมฟังหรอก
I'll do it.
ฉันจะรับผิดชอบเองค่ะ
Without using others' lives, I'll prove that I can do it.
ฉันจะพิสูจน์ให้ได้ว่า เราอยู่รอดได้โดยที่ไม่ต้องสละชีวิตใคร
Hooray! We made it out!
เยี่ยมไปเลย หนีออกมาได้แล้ว
We'll cut straight across the city!
เราจะขับผ่านตัวเมืองออกไป
We're going back to Ninannah.
พวกเราจะได้กลับนินันนากันแล้ว
I'm so happy to be able to see my parents again!
มีความสุขจัง มาชจะได้เจอพ่อจ๋าแม่จ๋าแล้ว
Will everyone be happy if they find out March is still alive?
ถ้าทุกคนรู้ว่ามาชยังมีชีวิตอยู่ จะดีใจกันไหมนะ
Of course, March!
แน่นอนอยู่แล้วละ มาช
You're a terrible driver.
เธอนี่ขับเกวียนไม่เป็นเลยนะ
Should I drive instead?
จะเปลี่ยนกันหน่อยไหม
Oh, these are the presents to give thanks.
นี่เป็นของขวัญขอบคุณที่ฉันทำไว้
I want to give them to big sister later.
เพื่อจะมอบให้พี่สาว
So keep it a secret for me.
ช่วยฉันเก็บเป็นความลับด้วยนะ
What's a secret?
ความลับอะไรเหรอ
Oh, nothing!
ไม่มีอะไร
Is that so?
จริงเหรอ
Hey March, what will you do once you've grown up?
พอมาชโตแล้วอยากทำอะไรเหรอ
March will do everything that she can do!
มาชอยากทำทุกอย่าง ที่ต้องโตเป็นผู้ใหญ่ก่อนถึงจะทำได้
First, March has to learn how to cook,
อย่างแรกคือทำอาหาร
or else she can't be a mother.
ต้องทำอาหารเป็นถึงจะเป็นแม่จ๋าได้
Then one day, when she has kids,
แล้วพอตอนที่มีลูก
she wants to make dolls for them like big sister does.
มาชอยากทำตุ๊กตาผ้าเหมือนที่พี่สาวทำให้ลูก
Also, March wants to learn more words.
ต้องเรียนคำศัพท์อีกหลาย ๆ คำ
And maybe even how to write.
แล้วก็ "ตัวอักษร" ด้วย
Maybe create a script for Ninannah...
สร้างตัวอักษรของนินันนาก็ดูน่าสนใจดี
Either way, March wants to know everything she doesn't know.
สรุปก็คือมาชอยากเรียนรู้สิ่งที่มาชยังไม่รู้
Growing up means learning and knowing more and more things, right?
เขาว่ากันว่า ยิ่งโตขึ้นสิ่งที่รู้ก็ยิ่งเพิ่มมากขึ้น
Of course, Fushi will be with me.
แน่นอนว่าฟุจังเองก็ต้อง
We'll learn together and grow up together.
เรียนรู้และเติบโตไปด้วยกันนะ
That wish will definitely come true, March.
ความปรารถนาของเธอจะเป็นจริงได้แน่ มาช
Big sister!
พี่สาว
It's all right.
ฉันไม่เป็นไร
This is a game as well.
นี่ก็เป็นเกมเหมือนกัน
A game of escaping before we're caught.
เกมที่จะไม่ถูกจับได้และหนีไปได้อย่างราบรื่น
Hand over the dog.
โปรดส่งเจ้าหมานั่นมาด้วยค่ะ
If you do so, I will spare your lives.
แล้วฉันจะไว้ชีวิตพวกคุณ
-No! -I refuse.
-ไม่ได้ -ฉันขอปฏิเสธ
Come at me! I'll knock you down!
เข้ามาสิ ฉันจะถีบให้ร่วงเลยคอยดู
No, big sister! It's too dangerous!
ไม่ได้นะพี่สาว มันอันตรายเกินไป
You'll get killed!
จะโดนฆ่าเอาได้นะ
What is it? Did something happen?
มีอะไร เกิดอะไรขึ้น
Please keep the wagon running!
ช่วยขับต่อไปด้วยค่ะ
Stand back, March!
มาช ถอยไป
Big sister, don't go!
พี่สาว อย่าไปนะ
What should March do?
มาชควรทำยังไงดี
What should I do?
จะทำยังไงดี
March wants to...
ฉันเองก็อยาก...
That's right. Come.
เยี่ยม เข้ามาเลย
Dog.
เจ้าหมาเอ๋ย
Mom, I'm so hungry I think I'm going to die...
แม่จ๋า หนูหิวจะตายอยู่แล้ว
Oh, don't worry.
น่าสงสารจังเลย
Mom will make food for you.
เดี๋ยวแม่จ๋าทำอาหารให้กินนะ
Making food!
ทำอาหาร ๆ
It's so good! Mom, your cooking is the best!
อร่อยมากเลย แม่จ๋าทำอาหารได้อร่อยจริง ๆ
Oh, you poor thing.
น่าสงสารจังเลย
Mom will make food for you right away.
เดี๋ยวแม่จ๋าทำอาหารให้กินนะ
Making food.
ทำอาหาร ๆ
Oh, you poor thing.
น่าสงสารจังเลย
Dad will be coming home early today, so I made a lot of food.
วันนี้พ่อจ๋าจะกลับบ้านเร็ว แม่จ๋าเลยจะทำอาหารอร่อย ๆ หลายอย่างเลย
Making food.
ทำอาหาร ๆ
Hey, why are you always alone?
พี่สาว ทำไมถึงชอบอยู่คนเดียวตลอดเลย
Well... I don't have any family.
เพราะฉันไม่มีครอบครัวน่ะ
Oh, right...
อ้อจริงสิ อันนี้...
For you.
ให้เธอแล้วกัน
Wait up a bit!
รอเดี๋ยวนะ
Here! Some food as thanks!
นี่ค่ะ ของขวัญขอบคุณ
Thank you...
ขอบใจนะ...
Chomp. Chomp.
อ้ำ ๆ ๆ
Wow, it's so tasty!
อร่อยมากเลย
Can't we be a family?
พวกเราเป็นครอบครัวเดียวกันได้ไหม
See, this is our child.
เขาเป็นลูกของพวกเรา
March will be the mom, and you can be the dad.
มาชเป็นแม่จ๋า พี่สาวเป็นพ่อจ๋า
March... March! March!
มาช...
March!
มาช
Big sister...
พี่สาว...
It'll be all right.
ไม่เป็นไรนะ
It'll be all right, March!
มาชต้องไม่เป็นอะไร
I'll fix you up right now!
เดี๋ยวฉันจะทำแผลให้นะ
Is March going to die for sister's sake?
มาชจะตายเพื่อพี่สาวไหม
No, March...
ไม่หรอกมาช
You're going to go back to the village and become an adult!
เธอจะได้กลับหมู่บ้าน จะได้โตเป็นผู้ใหญ่
This...
นี่เป็น...
For big sister... As a thank you...
ของขวัญขอบคุณ...ที่จะให้พี่สาว...
Big sister...
พี่สาว
Become a mother... in March's place.
ต้องเป็นแม่จ๋า...แทนมาชด้วยนะ
No, March! Isn't that your dream?
ไม่เอา นั่นเป็นความฝันของมาช
You need to become a mom!
เธอก็ต้องเป็นแม่จ๋าเองสิ
Isn't that right, March?
จริงไหมล่ะ มาช
Right?
จริงไหม
Look, it's finished!
ทำแผลเรียบร้อยแล้ว
Now, you'll be fine!
ทีนี้ก็ไม่เป็นอะไรแล้วนะ
All that's left to do is to go back!
เดี๋ยวพอกลับบ้านก็ดีขึ้นแล้ว
Big... sister...
พี่...พี่สาว...
Is Fushi... here?
ฟุจัง...อยู่ตรงนี้ไหม...
Yes.
อยู่สิ
That's... good...
ดีจังเลย...
Wow, this looks good.
ดูน่ากินมากเลย
Your cooking really is the best after all.
อาหารที่เธอทำนี่อร่อยที่สุดจริง ๆ ด้วย
Release the arrows!
ยิงได้
What's going on?
เกิดอะไรขึ้น
-It's the Spirit Bear! -The Spirit Bear has been angered!
-ท่านโอนิกุมะ -ท่านโอนิกุมะกำลังพิโรธ
Release the arrows!
ยิงได้
Fushi.
ฟุชิ
Thank you.
ขอบคุณนะ
You're fighting for March's sake, aren't you?
นายคงสู้เพื่อมาชสินะ
But it's all right now. You needn't fight anymore.
แต่ไม่เป็นไรแล้วละ ไม่จำเป็นแล้ว
March, I'm sorry for always coming home late because of work.
มาช ขอโทษนะ ฉันชอบทำงานจนดึกกว่าจะกลับบ้านได้
But today,
แต่ว่า วันนี้มันต่างออกไป
it seems like my work will be finished early.
ฉันควรรีบทำงานให้เสร็จ
Let's go back together now.
แล้วพาเธอกลับบ้านตอนนี้เลย
March?
มาช
Is that you, March?
มาช นั่นลูกจริง ๆ เหรอ
Yes, it's me!
มาชเองจ้ะ
Aren't you surprised that March is still alive?
ตกใจใช่ไหมล่ะ มาชยังไม่ตายนะ
It was so hard!
มันลำบากมากเลยละ
-That's great, March! -There, there.
-มาชเก่งมากเลย -เด็กดี
Mom, we're so hungry we feel like we're going to die!
แม่จ๋า พวกเราหิวจะตายอยู่แล้ว
Oh, don't worry.
น่าสงสารจังเลย
Mom will make food for all of you!
เดี๋ยวแม่จ๋าทำอาหารให้กินนะ
Hmm, how many are there?
ไหนดูสิ ทำกี่ที่ดีนะ
One, two, three, four...
มีทั้งหมด 1 2 3 4...
Hmm? Fushi?
แล้วฟุจังล่ะ...
Where am I?
ที่นี่คือที่ไหนกันนะ
That's right... I'm...
จริงสิ ฉันน่ะ...
Let's go back together now.
กลับไปด้วยกันนะ
Big sister.
พี่สาว
Fushi.
ฟุจัง
March is here! Right here!
มาชอยู่นี่ อยู่ตรงนี้ไง
No, no, no! March doesn't want to die!
แย่ที่สุด...มาชยังไม่อยากตายสักหน่อย
March is here! March isn't dead!
มาชอยู่ตรงนี้ มาชยังไม่ตาย
There are so many things March wants to do!
ยังมีอีกตั้งหลายอย่างที่มาชอยากทำ
And she hasn't done any of them yet!
มาชยังไม่ได้เริ่มทำอะไรเลยด้วยซ้ำ
It's all right, March.
ไม่ต้องห่วงนะมาช
Wait for me. I'll be there soon.
รออีกเดี๋ยวนะ ฉันจะตามไปหาเธอเอง
I'm not equipped to accept this reality...
ฉันไม่ได้เข้มแข็งพอที่จะยอมรับความจริงนี้
and continue to live on carefree.
และปิดหูปิดตามีชีวิตอยู่ต่อไปได้หรอก
No, big sister!
พี่สาว ไม่ได้นะ
You can't! Don't die!
ไม่ได้นะ ห้ามตายนะ
Fushi, stop her!
ฟุจัง รีบห้ามพี่เขาเร็ว
Help big sister!
รีบช่วยพี่สาวเร็วสิ
Stop!
ไม่นะ
Over there!
อยู่นั่นไง
Capture it while it's still in human form!
รีบจับมันตอนที่มันยังอยู่ในร่างคนเถอะ
And yet you tell me to keep on living.
นายจะบอกว่า ถึงจะเป็นแบบนี้ก็ควรมีชีวิตต่อไปงั้นเหรอ
What a distasteful guy...
นายมันแย่ชะมัดเลย
Parona!
พาโรน่า
That's...
นั่นมัน...
It can't be... The Spirit Bear!
ท่านโอนิกุมะเหรอ
Parona! Everyone was looking for you!
พาโรน่า ทุกคนต่างก็ตามหาเธออยู่
Where have you been for the past half-year?
ครึ่งปีมานี้ เธอไปอยู่ที่ไหนมา
I...
ฉัน...
couldn't do anything.
ทำอะไรก็ไม่สำเร็จสักอย่าง
That's right... This is for you.
อ้อ นี่เป็นจดหมาย
I was entrusted to give this letter to you.
ที่เขาฝากฉันมาให้พวกคุณ
A "letter"?
จดหมายเหรอ
It's a paper with words written on it.
กระดาษที่ใช้บันทึกข้อความ
Isn't this... just a hand print?
นี่มันก็แค่รอยมือนี่นา
What's written there is...
มันแปลว่า
"March is doing well".
"มาชสบายดี"
What have I done?
เป็นแบบนี้ไปได้ยังไงกัน
As her parent,
คนเป็นพ่อเป็นแม่อย่างเรา
I should've protected her...
ก็ควรต้องปกป้องมาชเอาไว้ให้ดีสิ
I'm... so sorry!
ขอโทษ...ขอโทษจริง ๆ
Thank you for fighting for March...
ขอบคุณสำหรับทุกสิ่งที่ทำเพื่อมาชนะ
The Yanome are here!
คนจากยาโนเมะกำลังมา
The Yanome? Why are they here?
ยาโนเมะเหรอ มาทำไมกัน
They must be after you.
เป้าหมายของพวกเขาคือนายแน่ ๆ
You have to run, Fushi.
ฟุชิ รีบหนีไปเร็ว
Avoid their scent and escape.
ตอนหนีต้องหลีกเลี่ยงกลิ่นของพวกนั้น
There is nobody to give your life meaning!
การเอาตัวรอดของตัวเองไม่ได้ได้มาจากคนอื่น
You must grasp it yourself!
แต่คือการเรียนรู้มันด้วยตัวเอง
You understand my words, right?
นายคงเข้าใจสิ่งที่ฉันพูดใช่ไหม
-Where are they? -Over there.
-อยู่ไหน -ตรงนั้นครับ
They're close.
เข้ามาใกล้มาก
Have they caught sight of Fushi?
พวกนั้นเห็นฟุชิแล้วเหรอ
I have to stop them.
ฉันต้องหยุดพวกเขาให้ได้
There's only this heavy, strong one.
เหลือแค่ธนูที่ทั้งหนักทั้งแข็งแรงคันนี้คันเดียว
That's fine.
แค่นี้ก็พอแล้ว
It hit!
เข้าเป้าแล้ว
No.
ไม่ใช่
I missed...
ฉันยิงพลาดไป
I missed!
ยิงพลาดไปต่างหาก
Having met and separated from its mother,
"เจ้าสิ่งนั้น" ได้พบเจอกับ "แม่" แต่ก็ต้องจากกันไป
"It" gained a sense of humanity.
และได้รับสัญชาตญาณความเป็นมนุษย์มา
No.
ไม่สิ
They never separated.
แท้จริงแล้วพวกเขาไม่ได้แยกจากกัน
They traveled on together.
แต่ได้ก้าวสู่การเดินทางไปด้วยกัน
Fushi reunited with Pioran
ฟุชิและปิโอลันได้พบกันอีกครั้ง
and began to learn the language and ways of living as a human
มันได้เรียนรู้ภาษาและวิธีใช้ชีวิตของมนุษย์
as he carried on his journey.
พร้อมกับเดินทางต่อไป
Suddenly, it was attacked by an unknown matter.
ในทันใดนั้นเองมันได้ถูกวัตถุนิรนามโจมตี
A being that could threaten its existence.
ศัตรูที่เป็ยภัยคุกคามต่อฟุชิ
"EPISODE SIX: OUR OBJECTIVE" A battle is about to begin.
"ตอนที่ 6 เป้าหมายของพวกเรา" การต่อสู้กำลังจะเริ่มขึ้น